The O
Azores B-LOC
( O
ə-ZORZ O
, O
also O
US B-GPE
: O
AY-zorz O
; O
Portuguese B-NORP
: O
Açores O
[ O
ɐˈsoɾɨʃ O
] O
) O
, O
officially O
the O
Autonomous B-LOC
Region I-LOC
of I-LOC
the I-LOC
Azores I-LOC
( O
Região O
Autónoma O
dos O
Açores O
) O
, O
is O
one O
of O
the O
two B-CARDINAL
autonomous O
regions O
of O
Portugal B-GPE
( O
along O
with O
Madeira B-LOC
) O
. O

It O
is O
an O
archipelago O
composed O
of O
nine B-CARDINAL
volcanic O
islands O
in O
the O
Macaronesia B-LOC
region O
of O
the B-LOC
North I-LOC
Atlantic I-LOC
Ocean I-LOC
, O
about B-QUANTITY
1,360 I-QUANTITY
km I-QUANTITY
( O
850 B-QUANTITY
mi I-QUANTITY
) O
west O
of O
continental O
Portugal B-GPE
, O
about B-QUANTITY
1,500 I-QUANTITY
km I-QUANTITY
( O
930 B-CARDINAL
mi O
) O
west O
of O
Lisbon B-GPE
, O
in O
continental O
Portugal B-GPE
, O
about B-QUANTITY
1,500 I-QUANTITY
km I-QUANTITY
( O
930 B-CARDINAL
mi O
) O
northwest O
of O
Morocco B-GPE
, O
and O
about B-QUANTITY
2,980 I-QUANTITY
km I-QUANTITY
( O
1,850 B-CARDINAL
mi O
) O
southeast O
of O
Newfoundland B-LOC
, O
Canada B-GPE
. O

Its O
main O
industries O
are O
agriculture O
, O
dairy O
farming O
, O
livestock O
, O
fishing O
, O
and O
tourism O
, O
which O
is O
becoming O
the O
major O
service O
activity O
in O
the O
region O
. O

In O
addition O
, O
the O
government O
of O
the O
Azores B-LOC
employs O
a O
large O
percentage O
of O
the O
population O
directly O
or O
indirectly O
in O
the O
service O
and O
tertiary O
sectors O
. O

The O
main O
city O
of O
the O
Azores B-LOC
is O
Ponta B-GPE
Delgada I-GPE
. O

There O
are O
nine B-CARDINAL
major O
Azorean B-NORP
islands O
and O
an O
islet O
cluster O
, O
in O
three B-CARDINAL
main O
groups O
. O

These O
are O
Flores O
and O
Corvo O
, O
to O
the O
west O
; O
Graciosa B-LOC
, O
Terceira B-LOC
, O
São B-LOC
Jorge I-LOC
, O
Pico B-LOC
, O
and O
Faial B-LOC
in O
the O
centre O
; O
and O
São B-LOC
Miguel I-LOC
, O
Santa B-LOC
Maria I-LOC
, O
and O
the O
Formigas B-LOC
Reef I-LOC
to O
the O
east O
. O

They O
extend O
for O
more B-QUANTITY
than I-QUANTITY
600 I-QUANTITY
km I-QUANTITY
( O
370 B-CARDINAL
mi O
) O
and O
lie O
in O
a O
northwest–southeast O
direction O
. O

All O
the O
islands O
have O
volcanic O
origins O
, O
although O
some O
, O
such O
as O
Santa B-LOC
Maria I-LOC
, O
have O
had O
no O
recorded O
activity O
since O
the O
islands O
were O
settled O
several B-DATE
centuries I-DATE
ago I-DATE
. O

Mount B-LOC
Pico I-LOC
, O
on O
the O
island O
of O
Pico B-LOC
, O
is O
the O
highest O
point O
in O
Portugal B-GPE
, O
at O
2,351 B-QUANTITY
m I-QUANTITY
( O
7,713 B-CARDINAL
ft O
) O
. O

If O
measured O
from O
their O
base O
at O
the O
bottom O
of O
the O
ocean O
to O
their O
peaks O
, O
which O
thrust O
high O
above O
the O
surface O
of O
the O
Atlantic B-LOC
, O
the O
Azores B-LOC
are O
among O
the O
tallest O
mountains O
on O
the O
planet O
. O

The O
climate O
of O
the O
Azores B-LOC
is O
very O
mild O
for O
such O
a O
northerly O
location O
, O
being O
influenced O
by O
its O
distance O
from O
the O
continents O
and O
by O
the O
passing O
Gulf B-LOC
Stream I-LOC
. O

Due O
to O
the O
marine O
influence O
, O
temperatures O
remain O
mild O
year-round O
. O

Daytime O
temperatures O
normally O
fluctuate O
between O
16 B-CARDINAL
° O
C O
( O
61 B-CARDINAL
° O
F O
) O
and O
25 B-CARDINAL
° O
C O
( O
77 B-CARDINAL
° O
F O
) O
depending O
on O
season B-DATE
. O

Temperatures O
above O
30 B-CARDINAL
° O
C O
( O
86 B-CARDINAL
° O
F O
) O
or O
below O
3 B-CARDINAL
° O
C O
( O
37 B-CARDINAL
° O
F O
) O
are O
unknown O
in O
the O
major O
population O
centres O
. O

It O
is O
also O
generally O
wet O
and O
cloudy O
. O

The O
culture O
, O
dialect O
, O
cuisine O
, O
and O
traditions O
of O
the O
Azorean B-NORP
islands O
vary O
considerably O
, O
because O
these O
remote O
islands O
were O
settled O
sporadically O
over O
a O
span O
of O
two B-DATE
centuries I-DATE
. O
= O
= O
History O
= O
= O
A O
small O
number O
of O
alleged O
hypogea O
, O
earthen O
structures O
carved O
into O
rocks O
that O
were O
used O
for O
burials O
, O
have O
been O
identified O
on O
the O
islands O
of O
Corvo B-LOC
, O
Santa B-LOC
Maria I-LOC
and O
Terceira B-LOC
by O
Portuguese B-NORP
archaeologist O
Nuno B-PERSON
Ribeiro I-PERSON
, O
who O
speculated O
that O
they O
might O
date O
back O
2000 B-DATE
years I-DATE
, O
implying O
a O
human O
presence O
on O
the O
island O
before O
the O
Portuguese B-NORP
. O

These O
kinds O
of O
structures O
have O
been O
used O
in O
the O
Azores B-LOC
to O
store O
cereals O
, O
however O
, O
and O
suggestions O
by O
Ribeiro B-PERSON
that O
they O
might O
be O
burial O
sites O
are O
unconfirmed O
. O

Detailed O
examination O
and O
dating O
to O
authenticate O
the O
validity O
of O
these O
speculations O
is O
lacking O
, O
thus O
it O
is O
unclear O
whether O
these O
structures O
are O
natural O
or O
man-made O
and O
whether O
they O
predate O
the O
15th-century O
Portuguese B-NORP
colonization O
of O
the O
Azores B-LOC

. O

= O
= O
= O
Discovery O
= O
= O
= O
The O
islands O
were O
known O
in O
the B-DATE
fourteenth I-DATE
century I-DATE
, O
and O
parts O
of O
them O
appear O
in O
the O
Catalan B-WORK_OF_ART
Atlas I-WORK_OF_ART
. O

In O
1427 B-DATE
, O
a O
captain O
sailing O
for O
Prince B-PERSON
Henry I-PERSON
the I-PERSON
Navigator I-PERSON
, O
possibly O
Gonçalo B-PERSON
Velho I-PERSON
, O
may O
have O
rediscovered O
the O
Azores B-LOC
, O
but O
this O
is O
not O
certain O
. O

In O
Thomas B-PERSON
Ashe's I-PERSON
1813 B-DATE
work O
, O
A B-WORK_OF_ART
History I-WORK_OF_ART
of I-WORK_OF_ART
the I-WORK_OF_ART
Azores I-WORK_OF_ART
, O
the O
author O
identified O
a O
Fleming B-NORP
, O
Joshua B-PERSON
Vander I-PERSON
Berg I-PERSON
of O
Bruges B-GPE
, O
who O
made O
landfall O
in O
the O
archipelago O
during O
a O
storm O
on O
his O
way O
to O
Lisbon B-GPE
. O

He O
stated O
that O
the O
Portuguese B-NORP
explored O
the O
area O
and O
claimed O
it O
for O
Portugal B-GPE
. O

Other O
stories O
note O
the O
discovery O
of O
the O
first B-ORDINAL
islands O
( O
São B-LOC
Miguel I-LOC
Island I-LOC
, O
Santa B-LOC
Maria I-LOC
Island I-LOC
and O
Terceira B-LOC
Island I-LOC
) O
by O
sailors O
in O
the O
service O
of O
Henry B-PERSON
the I-PERSON
Navigator I-PERSON
, O
although O
there O
are O
few O
documents O
to O
support O
the O
claims O
. O

Although O
it O
is O
commonly O
said O
that O
the O
archipelago O
received O
its O
name O
from O
açor O
( O
goshawk O
in O
Portuguese B-NORP
) O
, O
a O
common O
bird O
at O
the O
time O
of O
discovery O
, O
it O
is O
unlikely O
that O
the O
bird O
nested O
or O
hunted O
on O
the O
islands O

. O

= O
= O
= O
Settlement O
= O
= O
= O
There O
were O
no O
large O
animals O
on O
Santa B-LOC
Maria I-LOC
, O
so O
after O
its O
discovery O
and O
before O
settlement O
began O
, O
sheep O
were O
let O
loose O
on O
the O
island O
to O
supply O
future O
settlers O
with O
food O
. O

Settlement O
did O
not O
take O
place O
right O
away O
, O
however O
. O

Portuguese B-NORP
people O
weren't O
very O
interested O
in O
living O
on O
an O
isolated O
archipelago O
so O
far O
from O
civilization O
. O

Gonçalo B-PERSON
Velho I-PERSON
Cabral I-PERSON
patiently O
gathered O
resources O
and O
settlers O
for O
the B-DATE
next I-DATE
three I-DATE
years I-DATE
( O
1433 B-DATE
– O
1436 B-DATE
) O
, O
however O
, O
and O
sailed O
to O
establish O
colonies O
, O
first B-ORDINAL
on O
Santa B-LOC
Maria I-LOC
and O
then O
on O
São B-LOC
Miguel I-LOC
. O

Settlers O
cleared O
bush O
and O
rocks O
to O
plant O
crops O
: O
grain O
, O
grape O
vines O
, O
sugar O
cane O
, O
and O
other O
plants O
suitable O
for O
local O
use O
and O
of O
commercial O
value O
. O

They O
brought O
domesticated O
animals O
, O
such O
as O
chickens O
, O
rabbits O
, O
cattle O
, O
sheep O
, O
goats O
, O
and O
pigs O
, O
and O
built O
houses O
and O
established O
villages O
. O

The O
archipelago O
was O
largely O
settled O
from O
mainland O
Portugal B-GPE
. O

Portuguese B-NORP
settlers O
came O
from O
the O
provinces O
of O
Algarve B-LOC
, O
Minho B-LOC
, O
Alentejo B-LOC
and O
Ribatejo B-LOC
as O
well O
as O
Madeira B-LOC
. O

São B-LOC
Miguel I-LOC
was O
first B-ORDINAL
settled O
in O
1449 B-DATE
, O
the O
settlers O
– O
mainly O
from O
the O
Estremadura B-LOC
, O
Alto B-LOC
Alentejo I-LOC
and O
Algarve B-LOC
areas O
of O
mainland O
Portugal B-GPE
, O
under O
the O
command O
of O
Gonçalo B-PERSON
Velho I-PERSON
Cabral I-PERSON
– O
landed O
at O
the O
site O
of O
modern-day O
Povoação B-GPE
. O

Many O
of O
the O
early O
settlers O
were O
Portuguese B-NORP
Sephardic I-NORP
Jews I-NORP
who O
were O
banished O
/ O
exiled O
there O
by O
the O
inquisition O
on O
mainland O
Portugal B-GPE
- O
many O
had O
well O
known O
Sephardic B-NORP
surnames O
such O
as O
: O
Pereira B-PERSON
, O
Oliveira B-PERSON
, O
Cardoso B-PERSON
, O
Pimentel B-PERSON
, O
Pinto B-PERSON
, O
Rodrigues B-PERSON
, O
Mendes B-PERSON
, O
or O
Nunes B-PERSON
. O

In O
1522 B-DATE
, O
Vila B-GPE
Franca I-GPE
do I-GPE
Campo I-GPE
, O
then O
the O
capital O
of O
the O
island O
, O
was O
devastated O
by O
an O
earthquake O
and O
landslide O
that O
killed O
about B-CARDINAL
5,000 I-CARDINAL
people O
, O
and O
the O
capital O
was O
moved O
to O
Ponta B-GPE
Delgada I-GPE
. O

The O
town O
of O
Vila B-GPE
Franca I-GPE
do I-GPE
Campo I-GPE
was O
rebuilt O
on O
the O
original O
site O
and O
today B-DATE
is O
a O
thriving O
fishing O
and O
yachting O
port O
. O

From O
the O
first B-ORDINAL
settlement O
, O
the O
pioneers O
applied O
themselves O
to O
agriculture O
and O
by O
the B-DATE
15th I-DATE
century I-DATE
Graciosa B-LOC
exported O
wheat O
, O
barley O
, O
wine O
and O
brandy O
. O

The O
goods O
were O
sent O
to O
Terceira B-LOC
largely O
because O
of O
the O
proximity O
of O
the O
island O
. O

In O
1443 B-DATE
the O
island O
was O
already O
inhabited O
but O
active O
settlement O
only O
began O
with O
the O
arrival O
of O
the O
noble O
Flemish B-NORP
native O
Willem B-PERSON
van I-PERSON
der I-PERSON
Haegen I-PERSON
. I-PERSON

Arriving O
at O
Topo B-GPE
, O
where O
he O
lived O
and O
died O
, O
he O
became O
known O
as O
Guilherme B-PERSON
da I-PERSON
Silveira I-PERSON
to O
the O
islanders O
. O

João B-PERSON
Vaz I-PERSON
Corte-Real I-PERSON
received O
the O
captaincy O
of O
the O
island O
in O
1483 B-DATE
. O

By O
1490 B-DATE
, O
there O
were O
2,000 B-CARDINAL
Flemings B-NORP
living O
in O
the O
islands O
of O
Terceira B-LOC
, O
Pico B-LOC
, O
Faial B-LOC
, O
São B-LOC
Jorge I-LOC
and O
Flores B-LOC
. O

Because O
there O
was O
such O
a O
large O
Flemish B-NORP
settlement O
, O
the O
Azores B-LOC
became O
known O
as O
the B-LOC
Flemish I-LOC
Islands I-LOC
or O
the B-LOC
Isles I-LOC
of I-LOC
Flanders I-LOC
. O

His O
sister O
, O
Isabel B-PERSON
, O
was O
married O
to O
Duke B-PERSON
Philip I-PERSON
of I-PERSON
Burgundy I-PERSON
of O
which O
Flanders O
was O
a O
part O
. O

There O
was O
a O
revolt O
against O
Philip's B-PERSON
rule O
and O
disease O
and O
hunger O
became O
rampant O
. O

Isabel O
appealed O
to O
Henry B-PERSON
to O
allow O
some O
of O
the O
unruly O
Flemings B-NORP
to O
settle O
in O
the O
Azores B-LOC
. O

He O
granted O
this O
and O
supplied O
them O
with O
the O
necessary O
transportation O
and O
goods O
. O

The O
settlement O
of O
the O
then-unoccupied O
islands O
started O
in O
1439 B-DATE
with O
people O
mainly O
from O
the O
continental O
provinces O
of O
Algarve B-LOC
and O
Alentejo B-LOC
. O

In O
1583 B-DATE
, O
Philip B-PERSON
II I-PERSON
of O
Spain B-GPE
, O
as O
king O
of O
Portugal B-GPE
, O
sent O
his O
fleet O
to O
clear O
the O
Azores O
of O
a O
combined O
multinational O
force O
of O
adventurers O
, O
mercenaries O
, O
volunteers O
and O
soldiers O
who O
were O
attempting O
to O
establish O
the O
Azores B-LOC
as O
a O
staging O
post O
for O
a O
rival O
pretender O
to O
the O
Portuguese B-NORP
throne O
. O

Following O
the O
success O
of O
his O
fleet O
at O
the B-EVENT
Battle I-EVENT
of I-EVENT
Ponta I-EVENT
Delgada I-EVENT
captured O
enemies O
were O
hanged O
from O
yardarms O
, O
as O
they O
were O
considered O
pirates O
by O
Philip B-PERSON
II I-PERSON
. O

Opponents O
receiving O
the O
news O
variously O
portrayed O
Philip B-PERSON
II I-PERSON
as O
a O
despot O
or O
" O
Black B-PERSON
Legend I-PERSON
" O
; O
the O
sort O
of O
insult O
widely O
made O
against O
contemporary O
monarchs O
engaged O
in O
aggressive O
empire O
building O
and O
the B-EVENT
European I-EVENT
Wars I-EVENT
of I-EVENT
Religion I-EVENT
. O

An O
English B-NORP
raid O
of O
the O
Azores B-LOC
in O
1589 B-DATE
successfully O
plundered O
some O
harbouring O
ships O
and O
islands O
; O
a O
repeat O
eight B-DATE
years I-DATE
later I-DATE
, O
the B-EVENT
Islands I-EVENT
Voyage I-EVENT
, O
failed O
. O

Spain B-GPE
held O
the O
Azores B-LOC
under O
the O
" O
Babylonian B-EVENT
captivity I-EVENT
" O
of O
1580 B-DATE
– I-DATE
1642 I-DATE
. O

In O
the B-DATE
late I-DATE
16th I-DATE
century I-DATE
, O
the O
Azores B-LOC
and O
Madeira B-LOC
began O
to O
face O
problems O
of O
overpopulation O
. O

Spawning O
from O
that O
particular O
economic O
problem O
, O
some O
of O
the O
people O
began O
to O
emigrate O
to O
Brazil B-GPE

. O

= O
= O
= O
Iberian B-LOC
Union I-LOC
= O
= O
= O
Following O
the O
death O
of O
Henry B-PERSON
, O
the O
Cardinal-King O
of O
Portugal B-GPE
the O
nation O
fell O
into O
a O
dynastic O
crisis O
with O
various O
pretenders O
to O
the O
Crown O
of O
Portugal B-GPE
. O

Following O
his O
proclamation O
in O
Santarém B-LOC
, O
António B-PERSON
, I-PERSON
Prior I-PERSON
of I-PERSON
Crato I-PERSON
was O
acclaimed O
in O
the O
Azores B-LOC
in O
1580 B-DATE
( O
through O
his O
envoy O
António B-PERSON
da I-PERSON
Costa I-PERSON
) O
, O
but O
was O
expelled O
from O
the O
continent O
following O
the B-EVENT
Battle I-EVENT
of I-EVENT
Alcântara I-EVENT
. O

Yet O
, O
through O
the O
administration O
of O
Cipriano B-PERSON
de I-PERSON
Figueiredo I-PERSON
, O
governor O
of O
Terceira B-LOC
( O
who O
continued O
to O
govern O
Terceira B-LOC
in O
the O
name O
of O
ill-fated O
, O
former-king O
Sebastian B-PERSON
of O
Portugal B-GPE
) O
, O
the O
Azoreans B-NORP
resisted O
attempts O
to O
conquer O
the O
islands O
( O
including O
specifically O
at O
the B-EVENT
Battle I-EVENT
of I-EVENT
Salga I-EVENT
) O
. O

It O
was O
Figueiredo B-PERSON
and O
Violante B-PERSON
do I-PERSON
Canto I-PERSON
who O
helped O
organize O
a O
resistance O
on O
Terceira B-LOC
that O
influenced O
some O
of O
the O
response O
of O
the O
other O
islands O
, O
even O
as O
internal O
politics O
and O
support O
for O
Philip's B-PERSON
faction O
increased O
on O
the O
other O
islands O
( O
including O
specifically O
on O
São B-LOC
Miguel I-LOC
, O
where O
the O
Gonçalvez B-PERSON
da I-PERSON
Câmara I-PERSON
family O
supported O
the O
Spanish B-NORP
pretender O
) O
. O
The O
Azores B-LOC
were O
the O
last O
part O
of O
the B-LOC
Portuguese I-LOC
Empire I-LOC
to O
resist O
Philip's B-PERSON
reign O
over O
Portugal B-GPE
( O
Macau B-LOC
resisted O
any O
official O
recognition O
) O
, O
until O
the O
defeat O
of O
forces O
loyal O
to O
the O
Prior B-PERSON
of I-PERSON
Crato I-PERSON
with O
the O
Conquest B-EVENT
of I-EVENT
the I-EVENT
Azores I-EVENT
in O
1583 B-DATE
. O

Portuguese B-NORP
control O
with O
the O
end O
of O
the O
Iberian B-LOC
Union I-LOC
in O
1640 B-DATE
, O
and O
the O
beginning O
of O
the B-EVENT
Portuguese I-EVENT
Restoration I-EVENT
War I-EVENT
, O
not O
by O
the O
professional O
military O
, O
who O
were O
occupied O
with O
warfare O
on O
the O
Portuguese B-NORP
mainland O
, O
but O
by O
local O
people O
attacking O
a O
fortified O
Castilian B-NORP
garrison O

. O

= O
= O
= O
Liberal B-EVENT
Wars I-EVENT
= O
= O
= O
The B-EVENT
Portuguese I-EVENT
Civil I-EVENT
War I-EVENT
( O
1828 B-DATE
– O
1834 B-DATE
) O
had O
strong O
repercussions O
in O
the O
Azores B-LOC
. O

In O
1829 B-DATE
, O
in O
Praia B-GPE
da I-GPE
Vitória I-GPE
, O
the O
Liberals B-NORP
won O
over O
the O
absolutists B-NORP
, O
making O
Terceira B-LOC
Island I-LOC
the O
main O
headquarters O
of O
the O
new O
Portuguese B-NORP
regime O
and O
also O
where O
the B-ORG
Council I-ORG
of I-ORG
Regency I-ORG
( I-ORG
Conselho I-ORG
de I-ORG
Regência I-ORG
) O
of O
Maria B-PERSON
II I-PERSON
of O
Portugal B-GPE
was O
established O
. O

Beginning O
in O
1868 B-DATE
, O
Portugal B-GPE
issued O
its O
stamps O
overprinted O
with O
" O
AÇORES O
" O
for O
use O
in O
the O
islands O
. O

Between B-DATE
1892 I-DATE
and I-DATE
1906 I-DATE
, O
it O
also O
issued O
separate O
stamps O
for O
the O
three B-CARDINAL
administrative O
districts O
of O
the O
time O
. O

During O
the B-DATE
18th I-DATE
and I-DATE
19th I-DATE
centuries I-DATE
, O
Graciosa B-LOC
was O
host O
to O
many O
prominent O
figures O
, O
including O
Chateaubriand B-PERSON
, O
the O
French B-NORP
writer O
who O
passed O
through O
upon O
his O
escape O
to O
America B-GPE
during O
the O
French B-NORP
revolution O
; O
Almeida B-PERSON
Garrett I-PERSON
, O
the O
Portuguese B-NORP
poet O
who O
visited O
an O
uncle O
and O
wrote O
some O
poetry O
while O
there O
; O
and O
Prince B-PERSON
Albert I-PERSON
of I-PERSON
Monaco I-PERSON
, O
the B-DATE
19th I-DATE
century I-DATE
oceanographer O
who O
led O
several O
expeditions O
in O
the O
waters O
of O
the O
Azores O
. O

He O
arrived O
on O
his O
yacht O
Hirondelle B-FAC
, O
and O
visited O
the O
furna O
da O
caldeira O
, O
the O
noted O
hot O
springs O
grotto O
. O

